好了
There you go.
当时你饿了
There. You were hungry.
就是这样
That's it.
重复
Repeat.
先生 您好
Good day, sir.
祝您今天愉快
Good day to you.
您来休兰兹做什么事？
What brings you to Hewlands?
我正在给这些男孩们补习
I'm tutoring the boys here.
拉丁语家教
The Latin tutor.
我听说过你
I've heard of you.
是什么把你吸引到花园里来？
What brought you into the garden?
呃……
Uh...
这只是个问题 老师
It's just a question, master tutor.
是的 我 呃……
Yes, I, uh...
我想这里的空气一定很清新 而且……
I suppose the air was fresh out here, and...
呃 我看到你和你的鸟在一起了
uh, I saw you with your bird.
——是只鹰——啊
- It's a hawk. - Ah.
我可以？
May I?
不要靠得太近
Don't get too close.
他不认识你
He doesn't know you.
哦
Oh.
你好 男孩
Hello, boy.
啊
Ah.
他喜欢你
He likes you.
你叫什么名字？
What is your name?
我不会告诉你
I shan't tell you.
你必须这样做
You shall.
我不会
I shan't.
你应该这么做——我不会
- You shall. - I won't.
等我们接吻的时候你就会告诉我了
You'll tell me when we kiss.
你在干什么？
What are you doing?
艾格尼丝
Agnes.
我的名字叫艾格尼丝
My name is Agnes.
你从哪来？
Where are you from?
我说错话了吗？
Have I said something?
- 啊？ - 不
- Huh? - No.
你不知道我是谁——等等 我想见见……
- You don't know who I am. - Wait, I wish to see...
你再也见不到我了
You can't see me again.
哦
Oh.
你去哪儿了？
Where have you been?
我当时在田里帮巴塞洛缪干活
I was in the field helping Bartholomew.
一只刚出生的小羊羔生病了
A newborn lamb is unwell.
嗯 我……我去了田野
Well, I... I went to the field.
我没在那里看到你
I did not see you there.
我当时也在场告诉她 巴塞洛缪
Well, I was there. Tell her, Bartholomew.
她当时就在那里
She was there.
你见过那位新来的拉丁语家教吗？
Have you seen the new Latin tutor?
手套匠的儿子
The glover's son.
男孩们说他突然跑出去 就再也没回来
The boys said he just ran out, never returned.
他本应该给他们上课的
He was supposed to give them lessons
为了偿还他父亲的债务
to pay off his father's debts.
我没见过他
I haven't seen him.
唉 我真应该更谨慎些
Well, should've known better.
有其父必有其子
Like father, like son.
你知道 我确实相信你是
You know, I do believe you are
教区里最漂亮的女孩们
the prettiest girls in the parish.
我们是总有一天
-We are. -One day,
我会保持头脑清醒
I shall have my wits about me
献给所有前来追求你的人
for all the suitors that will come for you.
艾格尼丝是老大 她会第一个结婚
Agnes is the eldest. She'll marry first.
如果她继续往森林里跑 她就不会成功
She will not if she keeps running off to the forest
像吉普赛人一样
like a gypsy.
你去哪儿了？
Where have you been?
我们几个小时前就该见到你了
We were expecting you hours ago.
我当时……嗯？
- I was... - Well?
我当时在工作
I was working.
坐下坐下
Sit. Sit.
你的晚餐快凉了
Your supper's near cold.
- 呃 孩子们 孩子们！ - 嘿 - 停
- Uh, boys, boys! - Hey. -Stop.
足够所有人享用
There's enough for all.
在休兰兹的课程进行得怎么样？
How go the lessons at Hewlands?
那些男孩都不是学者
Those boys are no scholars.
我对学习这些东西感到好奇——嗯
I wonder at the notion of all that learning. -Hmm.
拉丁语中指那些注定只能当牧羊人的男孩
Latin for boys who will be naught but sheep farmers.
这是装腔作势——不 不 不！
- It is the putting on of airs. - No, no, no!
——这样就可以了！——好的 吉尔伯特
- That will do! - All right, Gilbert.
你听你妈妈说了 资源足够所有人用
You heard your mother. There's enough for all.
你诋毁休兰兹的男孩们
You speak ill of the boys at Hewlands.
“他们根本不是学者”
"They're no scholars."
但我告诉你
But I tell you something,
他们永远比你更有男子气概
they'll ever be more of a man than you are.
他们从事的是正当的工作 不像你
They are put to honest work, unlike you.
你那副浮夸的样子 毫无用处 毫无价值
Useless, tradeless, your fancy airs.
所有这些教育
All that education,
毫无道理可言
not an ounce of sense.
我辅导那些男孩是为了赚钱
I'm tutoring those boys to pay
你欠那家人的债 对吧？
your debts to that family, am I not?
你对那个家庭欠下了无法估量的债务
Your immeasurable amount of debt to that family.
我不是…… —— 住手！
- I'm not... - Stop!
那么 休兰兹庄园的其他家庭成员呢？你见过他们吗？
What of the rest of the family at Hewlands? Have you met them?
只有母亲
The mother only.
- 不是大女儿吗？ - 不是
- Not the eldest daughter? - No.
据说这个女孩是森林女巫的孩子
It is said the girl is the child of a forest witch.
我见过她 独自一人在乡间小路上徘徊
I've seen her, wandering the back roads alone
她手臂上停着一只鹰
with a hawk on her arm.
休兰兹有鹰吗？
A hawk at Hewlands?
是的
Yes.
他们说她独自一人带他去了森林
They say she takes him to the forest with her unaccompanied.
是啊 但是你确定吗 伊莱扎？
Yeah, but are you certain, Eliza?
大女儿养的是鹰 而不是女仆？
The eldest daughter keeps a hawk, not a servant girl?
是的没错
Yes. Yeah.
艾格尼丝
Agnes.
你好
Hello.
你在这里做什么？
What are you doing here?
给你带来了这个
Brought you this.
那是什么？
What is it?
呃……
It's, uh...
这是给你的鸟儿准备的新手套
it's a new glove for your bird.
我有一只手套
I have a glove.
艾格尼丝
Agnes.
艾格尼丝 等等
Agnes, wait.
我知道你是谁
I know who you are.
我是谁？
Who am I?
嗯 我……我不认识你 但我听说过一些事……
Well, I... I don't know you, but I've heard things...
我是森林女巫的女儿？
I'm the daughter of a forest witch?
是的 人们都这么说 但我不在乎……
Yes. People say that, but I-I don't care...
我是我母亲的女儿
I am my mother's daughter.
我从她身上学到了很多东西
I've learnt many things from her.
你在看什么？
What are you looking at?
你——为什么？
- You. - Why?
我……我以为你是一位能言善辩的人 我的导师
I... -I thought you were a man of words, master tutor.
是的
Yes.
难道不是吗？
Are you not?
我有时觉得和人交流很困难
Speaking with people is sometimes difficult for me.
那你就给我讲个故事吧
Well, tell me a story, then.
——一个故事？——是的
- A story? - Yes.
你想听什么样的故事？
What story would you like?
让你感动的事物
Something that moves you.
好的
All right.
你知道俄耳甫斯和欧律狄刻的故事吗？
Do you know the story of Orpheus and Eurydice?
奥菲斯是一位音乐家
Orpheus is a man of music.
他有一副非常动听的嗓音
He has this exquisite voice.
他演奏的基塔拉琴 是一种……
His playing of the kithara, which is a...
它是一种类似竖琴的里拉琴
is-is a harp-like lyre,
真是太神圣了
is so divine,
鸟类 那……
birds, the...
野兽 甚至石头和树木
the beasts, e-even the stones and the trees,
他们都随着他的音乐节奏舞动起来
they all moved to the rhythm of his music.
现在 俄耳甫斯爱上了这位美丽的仙女欧律狄刻
Now, Orpheus falls in love with this beautiful nymph, Eurydice.
他们结婚后不久
Soon after their marriage,
欧律狄刻被毒蛇咬了
Eurydice's bitten by a viper
毒素在她体内蔓延
and poison courses through her body,
她被杀了
and she's killed.
而奥尔甫斯 悲痛欲绝
And Orpheus, filled with grief,
前往冥界将她带回来
journeys to the underworld to take her back.
他迷住了这只三头犬 刻耳柏洛斯
He charms this three-headed dog, Cerberus.
他迷惑了哈迪斯 直到最后……
He beguiles Hades until finally...
他可以把他的爱人带回去
...he's allowed to take his love back with him
对生者的世界而言 但是……
to the world of the living but...
……但有一个条件
...under one condition.
那是什么？
What is it?
她必须跟在他后面
She must follow behind him,
他绝对不能回头看她
and he must not turn around to look at her.
现在 当他们开始攀登时
Now, as they begin their ascent,
奥菲斯听不到她的脚步声 所以他侧耳倾听……
Orpheus can't hear her footsteps, so he listens...
……然后听啊听啊听
...and listens and listens and listens.
但他只能听到自己的心跳声
But all he can hear is the sound of his heartbeat.
其余时间一片寂静
And the rest is silence.
当他接近冥界之门时……
And as he approaches the gates of the underworld...
他再也无法控制自己了
...he can't contain himself any longer.
他转过身去看她 而她……
He turns around to look at her, and she is...
永远被困在冥界
...trapped in the underworld forever.
唔
Hmm.
那真是一个好故事
That was a good story.
你喜欢它吗？
Did you like it?
艾草啊 记住你所带来的一切
Remember, mugwort, what you brought to pass,
你在Regenmeld准备了什么
what you readied at Regenmeld.
你的名字叫乌娜 是最古老的植物
You're called Una, the most ancient plant.
你敢违抗三 你敢违抗三十
You defy three, you defy 30,
你无惧毒液 你无惧空气传播疾病
you defy venom, you defy air illness,
你对抗着潜伏在这片土地上的恐怖
you defy the horror that stalks the land.
还有你 路边面包 植物之母
And you, waybread, plant mother,
你面向东方 内心却无比强大
you're open to the east yet mighty within.
马车从你身上缓缓驶过 女人们骑马从你身上经过
Carts creeped over you, women rode over you.
你挺过了这一切 并且进行了反击
You withstood it all, and you pushed back.
你真的了解一个人的一切吗？
Is it true that you know everything about a person
通过触摸这里？
by touching them here?
并非全部
Not everything.
当你触摸我这里的时候 你看到了什么？
When you touched me here, what did you see?
我看到了一幅风景
I saw a landscape.
- 你看到了风景？ - 嗯
- You saw a landscape? - Mm-hmm.
太空、洞穴、悬崖顶、
Spaces, caves, cliff tops,
隧道和海洋
tunnels and oceans,
这片深邃、黑暗、漆黑的虚空
this deep, dark, black void,
未被发现的国度
undiscovered countries.
她开口说话了……
She speaks...
她说话 她说话
She speaks, she speaks.
但是 柔软的
But, soft,
远处窗户透进来的是什么光线？
what light through yonder window breaks?
那是东方 朱丽叶是太阳
It is the east, and Juliet is the sun.
……然后杀戮……
...and kill...
嫉妒的月亮
...the envious moon.
你好
Hello.
我希望与你结为手牵手
I wish to be handfasted to you.
不 我……我必须与你结为伴侣
No, I... I must be handfasted to you.
其他人都不行
No one else will do.
我会和你的继母和你的哥哥谈谈
I-I will speak with your stepmother and your brother,
他们当然不会同意 但是……
and of course they will not agree, but...
我不在乎 因为我根本不擅长等待
I don't care because I have no talent for waiting.
我无法忍受等待
I cannot abide waiting.
你父母呢？
What about your parents?
你的父母永远不会同意
Your parents will never agree.
跟我来
Follow me.
等等等等等、等等
Wait. Wait. W-Wait.
不不！
- No! - No!
我的手套
My glove.
这是我母亲的手套——嗯
- This is my mother's glove. - Hmm.
她从树林里走了出来……
She came out of the woods...
就像她母亲一样
...like her mother
以及她的母亲
and her mother before her.
我家里的女性能看到一些东西……
The women in my family see things...
……而其他人却不这么认为
...that others don't.
艾格尼丝
Agnes.
罗文和年轻的艾格尼丝：记住 艾草
ROWAN and YOUNG AGNES: Remember, mugwort,
你在雷根梅尔德促成的事 你准备的事
what you brought to pass, what you readied at Regenmeld.
你的名字叫乌娜 是最古老的植物
You're called Una, the most ancient plant.
你敢违抗三 你敢违抗三十
You defy three, you defy 30,
你无惧毒液 你无惧空气传播疾病
you defy venom, you defy air illness,
你对抗着潜伏在这片土地上的恐怖
you defy the horror that stalks the land.
巴塞洛缪 它会痊愈的
Bartholomew, it will heal.
会留下疤痕吗？
Will it make a scar?
有可能这并非坏事
It may. That's no bad thing.
听
Listen.
你听到了吗？
Do you hear that?
艾格尼丝 你一定要重视你的梦境
You must pay attention to your dreams, Agnes.
他们会一直指引你
They will always guide you.
您好您好
- Good day. - Good day.
是的
Yes.
艾格尼丝 呃……
Agnes, what's, uh...
发生了什么事？
what's happened?
她母亲把她赶出了家门
Her mother has banished her from their house.
她不是我母亲
She's not my mother.
房子是我哥哥巴塞洛缪的
The house belongs to my brother, Bartholomew.
我选择离开
I chose to leave.
她怀孕了
She's with child.
哦
Oh.
它说这是你的
Says it's yours.
是吗？你的？——呃……
- Is it? Yours? - Uh...
她肚子里的孩子 是你放进去的吗？
The child in her belly, did you put it there?
我做了
I did.
母亲 我们已经结为盟约了我们绝不会允许这种事发生！
- We are handfasted, Mother. - We will never allow it!
- 这其中并无罪过- 恐怕你需要
- There is no sin in it. - I'm afraid you will need
——我们同意 而且我们会……——这没有错！
- our consent, and we will... - There is no sin in it!
——我们永远不会给！——好的！
- ...we will never give it, ever! - All right!
什么？
What?
你中了邪——不
- You've been bewitched. - No.
我宁愿你出海 也不愿你娶这个贱人
I'd rather you went to sea than marry this wench.
玛丽
Mary.
没必要那样
There's no need for that.
我毫不怀疑我们能够达成协议
I have no doubt we can come to an arrangement.
约翰嘘 女人
-John. -Hush, woman.
我相信你一定很渴望
I am certain you are eager
在婚礼仪式前见到你的妹妹
to see your sister before the altar.
我确信你宁愿不想见到你的儿子
I'm certain you'd rather not see your boy
被拖到淫秽法庭
dragged before the bawdy court.
没必要那样
There's no need for that.
他们说他们已经结为手牵手结婚了
They said they are handfasted.
只有我允许才行
Only if I say so.
但为什么要嫁给一个面色苍白的学者呢？
But why marry a pasty-faced scholar?
他有什么用？
What use is he?
他比我见过的任何男人都更有内涵
He's got more inside of him than any man I've ever met.
一切都将改变
Everything will change.
你你会改变的
You. You will change.
我已经开始改变了
I'm already changing.
里面太安静了
It's too quiet in there.
在哪儿？
In where?
那栋房子
That house.
如果我们感到害怕或犹豫不决 妈妈会对我们说什么？
What would our mother say to us if we were afraid or uncertain?
敞开心扉去生活
To live with our hearts open.
不要在黑暗中关闭它
To shut it not in the dark
但要把它转向太阳
but to turn it to the sun.
他爱的是我本来的样子 而不是我应该成为的样子
He loves me for what I am, not what I ought to be.
那你就嫁给他吧
Then marry him you shall.
谢谢
Thank you.
记住 艾草……
Remember, mugwort...
跟我一起说跟我一起说
Say it with me. Say it with me.
你所促成的事
What you brought to pass,
你在Regenmeld准备了什么
what you readied at Regenmeld.
你的名字叫乌娜 是最古老的植物
You are called Una, the most ancient plant.
你敢违抗三 你敢违抗三十
You defy three, you defy 30,
你无惧毒液 你无惧空气传播疾病
you defy venom, you defy air illness,
你对抗着潜伏在这片土地上的恐怖
you defy the horror that stalks the land.
看着我
Look at me.
艾格尼丝
Agnes.
啊
Ah.
哦
Oh.
嘿
Hey.
瞧瞧那火！
Look at that. Look at the fire.
嗯？那是什么？
Mmm, what's that?
小狗拖进来了什么东西
The doggy dragged something in.
有件事发生了
There's something.
哦
Oh.
爸爸来了
Daddy's coming.
你好
Hello.
针脚需要更小一些
Stitches need to be smaller.
M-小得多
M-Much smaller.
是的
Yes.
唔
Hmm.
无用
Useless.
好了 现在……
Okay, and now...
更小
smaller.
你要去哪里？ —— 我要去
- Where are you going? - I'm going.
回去工作
Get back to work.
那是你最后一次打我了
That was the last time you will ever hit me.
你明白吗？
Do you understand?
你明白了吗？！——明白了
- Do you understand?! - Yes.
亲爱的 你该回床上睡觉了
My love, you should come back to bed.
你在写什么？
What are you writing?
没什么特别的
Nothing of note.
这绝非小事
It's never nothing.
我不知道
I don't know.
或许等它完工后 就会……
Perhaps when it's finished, it will...
或许等它完工之后吧
Perhaps when it's finished.
你为什么不把你写的东西读给我听？
Why don't you read me what you've written?
A-艾格尼丝 不是——
A-Agnes, it's not--
它——它还没完成
It-It's not finished.
还没结束
It's not finished.
别这样 你会吵醒宝宝的
Stop it. You'll wake the baby.
没关系
It's okay.
不
No.
对不起
I'm sorry.
我喝得太多了 呃……
I've had too much, uh...
艾格尼丝 我喝太多了
Agnes, I've had too much to drink.
我曾有过……
I've had...
我喝太多了
I've had too much to drink.
嘿
Hey.
那是什么？
What is it?
把手给我
Give me your hand.
求求你 求求你 求求你 求求你
Pl-Pl-Please, please, please, please,
求求你 求求你 求求你
please, please, please, please.
你害怕我会看到什么？请住口
- What are you afraid I will see? - Please stop.
我是一个暴力且危险的人
That I am a violent and dangerous man.
不 你都不是那种人
No, you are none of those things.
你怎么知道？——你是个好人你是个……
- How do you know? - You're a good man. You're a...
你是个好人
You are a good man.
You're a good man.
你是希望我们从未结婚吗？
Is it that you wish that we never wed?
你怎么能说出这样的话？
How could you say such a thing?
你和苏珊娜是我活着的全部意义
You and Susanna are all that I live for.
这就是我活着的意义
All that I live for.
那它到底是什么？
What is it, then?
- 看着我- 住手！
- Here. Look at me. - Just stop!
停下 停下求求你 求求你 求求你 求求你 求求你
Stop, stop. Please, please, please, please, please, please.
看着我
Look at me.
听着听着听着
Listen. Listen. Listen.
我迷路了
I'm lost.
我丢了我的……
I've lost my...
我迷路了
I've lost my way.
我只是需要——呃 艾格尼丝 我只是需要工作
I just need to-- uh, Agnes, I just need to work.
他没睡着
He's not sleeping.
他有没有对你发过脾气？——没有
Has he ever lost his temper with you? -No.
- 如果他举手…… - 不 他从来没有举手过
- If he raises a hand... - No, he has never.
他从来没有他是在生自己的气
He's never. He's angry with himself.
他对自己感到厌恶
He's sick with himself.
他是个好人
He's a good man.
他是个好丈夫 也是个好父亲
He's a good husband, he's a good father,
但他还需要更多
but he n-needs more.
除了家人和你 他还需要什么呢？
What could he possibly need other than his family and you?
他有你他需要去伦敦
- He has you. - He needs to go to London.
- 伦敦？ - 是的
- London? - Yeah.
为什么选择伦敦？——因为伦敦是全世界汇聚的地方
Why London? -Because London is where the whole world gathers.
或许他可以把父亲的生意拓展到那里
Perhaps he could extend his father's business there.
哦 你又操之过急了谁知道他会是什么样的人呢……
- Oh, you're being hasty again. - Who knows what he may be...
我并非操之过急他还需要更多
I'm not being hasty. He needs more.
- 他需要一份正经工作- 他不属于这个世界
- Well, he needs proper work. - He's not of this world.
这个人需要一份正经工作
The man needs proper work.
这个小镇上有什么？——他不可能就这么逃走
- What's in this little town? - He can't just run away.
这条小生命？这个小东西 它会……
This little life? This little thing, it'll...
……碾碎他
...crush him.
他需要和父亲保持距离
He needs distance from his father.
你会和他一起去伦敦吗？
And you would go with him to London?
不 我会等到他安顿下来
No, I'll wait until he's settled.
很快我们就会有更多的人加入
There'll be more of us soon.
——还要再要一个孩子？——是的到夏末的时候
- Another child? - Yes. By summer's end.
那么现在还不是把他送走的时候
Then now is not the time to send him away.
我会失去他
I'll lose him.
我感觉我快要失去他了
I'm already losing him.
如果你把他送走 你会失去他的
You'll lose him if you send him away.
不 我知道 我知道我们的爱会让我们保持稳定
No, I know, I know that our love will keep us steady.
拜托了您能跟他父亲谈谈吗？
Please. Will you speak to his father?
如果你建议他去伦敦 他会听你的
He'll listen to you if you suggest him going to London.
请
Please.
我应该找个住处
I should find lodgings.
靠近河流 靠近制革厂
Be near the river, close to the tanneries.
但我听说河水水流湍急 很危险
But I'm told that the currents in the river are dangerous
而且你必须雇佣一位经验丰富的船夫
and that you must engage an experienced boatman
每次你过马路 我都会这么做
every time you cross, and I'll be certain to do that
我保证 每次都是如此
every time, I promise.
我会想念你和苏珊娜
And I will think of you and Susanna
随着时间的流逝
with every passing moment.
我会在伦敦帮我们找住处
And I will find us lodgings in London,
我们终将再次团聚
and we shall all be together again.
你还是不知道是男孩还是女孩吗？
Do you still not know if it's a boy or a girl?
不
No.
不知道为什么
Don't know why.
你不是说过你永远都会有两个孩子吗？
Have you not said that you would always have two children?
是的
Yes.
临终前 我的床边有两个孩子
Two children at my deathbed.
那么 这是第二个
Well, then, here is the second.
我们不会说再见——不
- We won't say goodbye. - No.
走——走
Get-- Go.
你要去哪儿？ —— 不 我只是……
- You going somewhere? - No, I'm just...
是的 我要去湖边……
Yes, I'm going to the lake...
你不会去森林
You're not going to the forest.
我必须这么做——不 你不能这么做吉尔伯特！
- I must. - No, you must not. Gilbert!
你……你必须让我去那里
You... you have to let me go there.
让我去那里！——艾格尼丝小姐
- Let me go there! - Miss Agnes.
你必须放我走！河水决堤了！
- You must let me go! - The river has burst its banks!
- 没办法…… - 让我来！
- There is no way... - Let me!
根本没办法进森林——让我进去！不！
There's no way to get to the forest. -Let me! No!
我们已经为你准备好了一切——我的宝贝！
We have everything ready for you. -My baby!
不 我的宝贝
No, my-my baby.
我不能
I can't.
我不会在这个房子里生孩子
I will not have my baby in this house.
在我家不行
Not in this house.
不
No.
河流
The river.
嘘 嘘 嘘 嘘嘘不 不 不 不
- Hush, hush, hush, hush. Hush. - No, no, no, no.
他谈到了那条河
He spoke about the river.
这条河很危险他可能会被水流冲走！
The river is dangerous. He may be swept downstream!
艾格尼丝艾格尼丝艾格尼丝
Agnes. Agnes. Agnes.
艾格尼丝 他一切都好
Agnes, all is well with him.
你不记得他最后一封信了吗？
Do you not recall his last letter?
停止尖叫
Stop the screaming.
你会吵醒全镇的人
You'll wake the whole town.
他听起来……
He sound...
他的声音听起来不一样了
He sounded different.
不 他给我们带来了好消息
No, he had good news for us.
剧院 剧院
- The theater. - Theater.
他与球员们签有合同
He has a contract with the players
为剧院制作手套
to make gloves for the theater.
为了手套为了手套
For the gloves. For the gloves.
艾格尼丝 安静点
Agnes, hush now.
嘘 嘘 嘘
Hush. Hush. Hush.
向下冲向下冲
Bear down. Bear down.
啊！哦！
Ah! Ooh!
——找到了——是个男孩
- There we go. -It's a boy.
好了
There we go.
好孩子好孩子
Good boy. Good boy.
是个男孩
It's a boy.
我的孩子
My boy.
谢谢
Thank you.
这是什么？发生了什么事？
What is it? What's happening?
她要重新开始了
She's starting again.
- 你怀的是双胞胎 我的女儿- 来吧 伊莱扎
- You're having twins, my girl. -Come on, Eliza.
快点
Here. Quickly.
带走他
Take him.
不 不
No, no.
两个人站在我的床边 等待我的死亡
Two standing at my deathbed.
我一直相信会是这样……
I always believed that it would be...
他们会成为我的孩子
that they would be my children.
现在……
And now...
现在我明白了 那个人会是你
now I see it will be you.
我们需要扶你到凳子上去
We need to get you to the stool.
它来了它就在这里
It's coming. It's here.
不——快起来快起来起来 起来
- No. - Come on. Come on up. Up, up.
我不能……我……
I can't... I...
我不能
I can't.
走吧我真不该那样……
- Go. - I should never have...
我不能……
I can't...
我去不了
I can't make it.
我错了我错了
I got it wrong. I got it wrong.
我得到了它...
I got it...
他……他不在
He... He's not here.
He's... He's not here.
艾格尼丝 你可以……
Agnes, you can...
你必须这样做
and you must.
我不能
I cannot.
艾格尼丝
Agnes.
你可以...
You can...
你会的
and you will.
你丈夫就出生在这个房间里
Your husband was born here in this room.
他在那里 在窗边 吸入了第一口空气
He took his first breath there by the window.
请
Please.
请放过这个孩子
Please let this child live.
放过这个孩子吧求求你们了
Let this child live. Please.
你会让他……
Will you let him...
让他回来和他的孩子在一起吧
Let him come back and be with his child.
请
Please.
愿他永远对我抱有善意
Let him think kindly of me always.
记住账号
Remember me.
妈妈
Mama.
妈妈？
Mum?
太弱了
Just too weak.
她太痛苦了
She was in too much pain.
我的意思是 可怜的女人
I mean, poor woman.
她变得越来越虚弱
She just got weaker and weaker.
我的意思是 有时候事情就是这样
I mean, that's just the way of it sometimes.
她——她一定知道末日将至
She-she must have known the end was nigh.
最好不要在孩子们面前提起她
Best not speak of her to the children.
换个母亲更安全
Safer with a different mother.
还这么年轻
So young.
他们可能不记得她了
They may not remember her.
妈妈！——艾格尼丝艾格尼丝
- Mum! - Agnes. Agnes.
妈妈 不要！ 不 不要艾格尼丝
- Mama, no! - No, no. Agnes.
孩子孩子
Child. Child.
妈妈 不要！不 不 不不——不
- Mummy, no! - No, no, no. Ch-Ch-Ch-- No.
不 不
- No! - No.
不 让我见见她！不 不！
- No, let me see her! - No, no!
让我见见她！ 不！
- Let me see her! - No!
不 妈妈！
No, Mama!
艾格尼丝——不！
- Agnes. - No!
妈妈我想要 我想要我的妈妈
Mum. I want, I want my mum.
我想要我的……
I want my...
哦！来了！是个女孩！
Oh! Here we go! It's a girl!
是个女孩她……
It's a girl. She's...
等等……
It's... Wait.
快点 快点
Come on. Come on.
她为什么不哭？
Why is she not crying?
她已经不在人世了
She lives not.
把她给我吧
Let me have her.
你不应该看她 那样会带来厄运
You should not look upon her. It's bad luck.
把她给我
Give her to me.
我会确保它得到体面的安葬
I'll make sure it gets a decent burial.
把我的孩子还给我！
Give me my child!
我的孩子
My child.
艾格尼丝 你生了个男孩
Agnes, you have a baby boy.
让我把他带到你面前 你来喂他
Let me bring him to you, and you may feed him.
女孩已经升入天堂了
The girl has gone to heaven.
她并没有上天堂
She's not gone to heaven.
母亲去世的那晚 我许下了一个誓言
I made a vow the night my mother died.
我会去你们的教堂 但我不会在那里说一个字
I will go to your church, but I shan't say a word there.
是的是的
Yes. Yes.
你会活下去
You will live.
我会确保没有任何东西能把你带走
I will make sure nothing ever takes you away.
我实在找不到
I actually couldn't find it.
唔
Hmm.
这里
Here.
完美的
Perfect.
我找到我的帽子了
I found my hat.
好的是的
Okay. Yes.
好 就站在那边站在那边
Okay, take that side. Take that side.
是的
Yeah.
把它放在这附近
And put it around here.
完美的
Perfect.
哦 对不起让我来帮你吧
- Ooh. Sorry. - Let me help you.
它顺着我的脸流下来了
It's down my face.
我是哈姆内特 我是哈姆内特
- I'm Hamnet. - I'm Hamnet.
我是朱迪思 我是朱迪思
- I'm Judith. - I'm Judith.
这栋房子里不许跑步
There will be no running in this house.
请各位举止得体……
Conduct yourselves, please, as...
女士们和先生们
gentlewomen and gentlemen.
你要去哪里？
Where are you going?
是啊 他……他来了 他来了
Yeah. He's-he's coming. He's coming.
你好
Hello.
我们都知道他们交换过衣服
We all know they've swapped clothes.
我们还要假装不知道多久？
How long are we going to pretend we don't?
只要他们还认为自己是一样的 我们就会一直假装
We'll pretend for as long as they think they're the same.
你好
Hi.
父亲 您能帮我研读这段希腊文吗？
Father, will you help me with the Greek passage
昨天课上讲的？
from yesterday's lesson?
哈姆内特 我还以为你已经学会了呢
Hamnet, I thought you'd already learnt it.
我没带 因为我把入门教材落在学校了
I didn't because I left my primer at school.
哈姆内特
Well, Hamnet,
你需要认真对待学业
you need to take your studies seriously.
如果你不……你又怎能指望进步呢？
How do you expect to improve if you're not...
你们这些坏家伙
You rascals.
- 我们骗了你吗？ - 当然骗了
- Did we trick you? - Of course you did.
你又跟我换了身份来骗我
You swapped places to hoodwink me again.
苏珊娜 过来一下
Susanna, come here.
过来
Come here.
现在 你还记得那件事吗？
Now, do you remember the thing
我们原本打算为你母亲做什么？
we were going to do for your mother?
是啊——你还记得吗？你准备好了吗？——是的
Yeah. -You remember? You ready to do it? -Yeah.
好的快出去
Okay. Go outside quickly.
走 走 走 走 走 走 走 走 走 走 走 走
Go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go, go.
- 朝那边走一步…… - 等等
- Just step toward... - Wait.
一——向右走迈步
One st-- Come to your right. Step.
再走一步
Step. One more.
还有一个
One more.
我们三人何时再见面？
When shall we three meet again?
雷雨交加？
In thunder, lightning or in rain?
当喧嚣散去 当战斗的胜负已分！
When hurly-burly's done, when the battle's lost and won!
那将是日落之时
That will be ere at set of sun.
- 地点在哪？ - 在荒原上
- Where the place? - Upon the heath.
去见艾格尼丝
There to meet with Agnes.
我来了 格雷马尔金
I come, Graymalkin.
牧场呼唤
Paddock calls.
匿名！
Anon!
公平即丑陋 丑陋即公平
Fair is foul and foul is fair.
公平即丑陋 丑陋即公平公平即丑陋 丑陋即公平
Fair is foul and foul is fair. Fair is foul and foul is fair.
公平即丑陋 丑陋即公平
Fair is foul and foul is fair.
悬停在……
Hover through the...
做得好！
Well done!
太棒了！
That was amazing!
挖深一些 然后把所有东西都移到一边
Dig it deep, and then you move all of it to the side,
然后把它放在这里
and then you put it down here.
对吧？然后把四周的土也填上
Right? And then you get the soil around the sides,
然后你再轻轻拍拍它
and then you pat it more.
然后你就会看到类似这样的片段
And then you get bits like that.
然后把它揉搓在手上
And you rub it in your hands.
哇哦然后又回来了！
Whoa. And then back!
这样做
Do this.
当你这样做的时候 画圈
And when you're doing this, circle.
对 就是这样
Yeah, like that.
准备好？
Ready?
前进后退
Forward. And back.
现在 格挡 格挡 格挡
Now, parry, parry, parry.
很好又一次
Good. Again.
现在 做完这个之后 我要做这个
Now, after that one, I'm gonna do this,
然后你赶紧让开
and you get out of the way.
准备好了吗？围成一圈挥舞你的剑
Ready? Circle off. Spin your sword.
不
No.
画圈 旋转你的剑
Circle, spin your sword.
现在 请上前来
Now, come forward.
然后回去
And go back.
一二三
One, two three.
让开！
Out of the way!
非常好再次强调
Very good. Again.
朱迪思 这个叫什么名字？
Judith, what's this one called?
百里香百里香——迷迭香
-Thyme. Thyme. - Rosemary.
百里香百里香百里香——百里香百里香
-Thyme. Thyme. Thyme. - Thyme. Thyme.
- 我搞混了 - 没关系
- I got it mixed up. - That's okay.
这个...
This one...
-那是迷迭香-是的
-Now, that's rosemary. -Yeah.
迷迭香有什么用途？
And what is rosemary for?
把它放进苹果里——苹果
- Putting it in apples. -Apples.
不迷迭香是做什么用的？
No. Rosemary's for?
回忆
Remembering.
现在 你要把这些都揉进手里
Now, you're to rub all this in your hands.
你吹了一小口愿望
You blow a little wish.
祝他一路顺风
To wish him on his way.
是吗？这是你和他之间的秘密
Yeah? And it's your secret with him.
你看到他了吗？
Did you see him?
你没看到他在天上吗？
Did you not see him in the sky?
好的 再来一次
All right, do it again.
再许个愿吧
Make another wish.
看 就在上面
Look. Right up there.
你看 他就在那儿你看到他了吗？
Look, just there. Did you see him?
他把你的所有愿望都珍藏在他那颗小小的心里
And he's got all your wishes tucked in his little heart.
所以 每当你想要缅怀他的时候
So any time that you want to remember him,
你只需要去……
you just have to go...
你要去哪里？
Where are you going?
咦？我一定要抓住你！
Huh? I'm gonna catch you!
我一定会抓住你的！
I'm gonna catch you!
父亲？
Father?
一切都好吗？
Is all well?
是的
Yes.
听着 我希望你远离你爷爷
Listen, I want you to stay away from your grandfather.
他不会打你的姐妹 但我担心的是你
He'll not hit your sisters, but it's you that I worry for,
我需要知道 当我不在你身边的时候 你也能安全无虞
and I need to know that you'll be safe when I'm not here.
你要再回伦敦吗？
You're going back to London again?
是的 明天
Yes, tomorrow.
明天？
Tomorrow?
没关系
It's all right.
这次我们跟你一起去吗？
Will we go with you this time?
不 还没有
No, not yet.
嘿
Hey.
我会想念你
I'll miss you.
但我必须走了 你明白吗？我……
But I have to go, you understand? I...
我知道
I know.
我明白
I understand.
那挺好的
That's good.
因为我需要你照顾好你的母亲和姐妹们
'Cause I need you to look after your mother and your sisters.
你会这么做吗？
Will you do that?
是的
Yes.
你会勇敢吗？——是的
- Will you be brave? - Yes.
是的？
Yes?
你会勇敢吗？——是的
- Will you be brave? - Yes.
你敢吗？！
Will you be brave?!
啊？！是的！是的 我会勇敢的！
- Huh?! - Yes! Yes, I'll be brave!
我会勇敢的我会勇敢的
I'll be brave. I'll be brave.
我在伦敦看过房子了
I've looked at houses for us in London.
秋天来了——嗯
-Autumn is coming. - Mm.
孩子们会生病
And the children will fall ill.
朱迪思 她还不够坚强
Judith, she's still not strong enough.
她经常感到胸闷
She often gets congestion in her chest.
伦敦的空气……
And the air in London is...
我们不能
We can't.
但不久的将来 我们会实现这个愿望
But one day soon, we will.
我们将和你们一起去伦敦
We will come to London with you.
不 你不会的
No, you won't.
你永远不会来
You'll never come.
你一直盼望着盛夏的酷暑过去……
You've waited for the heat of summer to pass...
秋季的干燥
...the dryness of autumn,
雪和寒冷
the snow and the cold.
你不相信朱迪丝能在伦敦活着离开
You do not believe that Judith will ever survive London.
你会竭尽全力让那个孩子活下去
You'd do anything in your power to keep that child alive.
难道这不是母亲应该做的吗？
Isn't that what a mother is supposed to do?
当然是这样
Of course it is.
所以...
So...
我决定在斯特拉特福德以外的地方找块地
...I've decided to look for land outside Stratford.
你应该带着孩子们住在那里
That's where you should live with the children.
- 谢谢 - 嗯
- Thank you. - Mm-hmm.
哦！
Ooh!
她在哪儿？啊！
Where is she? Ah!
哈姆内特他就在那里
Hamnet. There he is.
过来
Come here.
我爱你我爱你我爱你
I love you. I love you. I love you.
好的爱你
All right. Love you.
来吧——我爱你
- Come on. - Love you.
爱你
Love you.
哦
Oh.
好的 过来
All right. Come here.
- 记住我跟你说过的话 好吗？ - 好的
- Remember what I told you, okay? - Okay.
好孩子
Good boy.
再见再见
- Bye. - Bye.
哈姆内特？
Hamnet?
哦
Oh.
过来 过来
Come on. Come here.
把你的手牌给我看看
Show me your hand.
什么？你看到了什么？
What? What do you see?
我看见你
I see you.
长大了
Grown.
而且非常强壮
And very strong.
我看到你在伦敦和你父亲一起工作
And I see you in London working with your father.
- 在剧院吗？ - 是的
- In the theater? - Yes.
在剧院
At the playhouse.
我将要做什么？
What will I be doing?
哈姆内特 你想做什么？
What do you wish to do, Hamnet?
我应该是一名持剑的玩家
I should be one of the players with a sword.
一把剑？
A sword?
是的
Yes.
我将用它与对方的剑进行碰撞
And I shall clash it against the sword of the other player.
给我看看
Show me.
将会有一场恶战
There'll be a terrible fight,
所有观看的人都会吓得魂飞魄散
and everybody watching will be frightened out of their wits.
谁将获胜？
And who will win?
我当然会
I shall, of course.
当然应该
Of course you shall.
他们似乎有什么心事
Something has upset them.
会是什么呢？
What could it be?
天气？
The weather?
或许是空气中有什么异味？
Something in the air, perhaps?
最好告诉琼今天让孩子们待在家里
Best tell Joan to keep the children inside today.
哈姆内特·朱迪思？
HAMNET Judith?
朱迪思？
Judith?
你在哪里？
Where are you?
醒醒！
Wake up!
面包师告诉我 她的猫生了小猫
The baker told me her cat had kittens.
我们需要亲眼看看
We need to see them.
有八个 朱迪思八个！
There's eight, Judith. Eight!
我们得快点 要下雨了
We need to hurry. It's going to rain.
朱迪思？
Judith?
裘德？
Jude?
怎么了？
What's wrong?
朱迪思 你怎么了？
What's wrong, Judith?
朱迪思 回答我
Judith, answer me.
朱迪思 醒醒
Judith, wake up.
朱迪思 拜托了朱迪思
Judith, please. Judith.
- 是什么人？ - 是朱迪思
- What is it? - It's Judith.
她这样多久了？
How long has she been like this?
自从我放学回来之后
Since I returned from school.
艾格尼丝：我的天哪
AGNES Oh, my God.
她明白了
She's got it.
难道不是吗？
Hasn't she?
她得了瘟疫
She's got the pestilence.
对吧 妈妈？
Hasn't she, Mama?
去找你奶奶
Go find your grandmother.
叫她过来
Bid her to come.
现在！
Now!
她感觉浑身发热
She's burning up.
我们需要 嗯 更多的水
We need, um, more water.
把火烧得更大些 把水烧得更热些
Make a bigger fire and heat up more water.
我们需要热水——伊莱扎 再去打些水来
- We need warm water. -Eliza, fetch more water
把贝利斯从厨房端出来
and bring the Bellis from the kitchen.
一排肉桂
A row of cinnamon.
肉桂有驱暑的功效
Cinnamon, that's good for drawing out the heat.
松针草或芸香百里香 没错
Pineweed or a rue. Thyme, yes.
你会在房间里找到它们
You'll find them in the room.
妈妈嗯——另一张桌子另一边
Mama. Yeah. -The other table. The other side.
是的 妈妈在这里 我的宝贝
Yeah, Mama's here, my love.
来 喝这个这是迷迭香果冻做的
Here, drink this. It's rosemary and jelly.
一切都会好起来的 嗯？
All will be well, hmm?
一切都会好起来的
All will be well.
朱迪思 留下来
Judith, stay with.
妈妈在这里没事的妈妈在这里
Mama's here. It's okay. Mama's here.
大黄我们需要大黄来清肠胃
Rhubarb. We need rhubarb to purge the stomach,
驱除瘟疫
drive out the pestilence.
你能去拿一些吗？
Can you go and fetch some?
妈妈来了没事的朱迪思 我们都在这里
Mama's here. It's okay. Judith, we're all here.
苏珊娜 你也去打些水
Susanna, draw some water, too.
哈姆内特和……还有玛丽和苏珊娜
Hamnet and... and Mary and Susanna.
尽快取水
Draw water as soon as you can.
他为什么没来？
Why isn't he here?
伊莱扎 去给你哥哥写信 让他过来
Eliza, go write to your brother and tell him to come.
朱迪思
Judith.
张开嘴 朱迪思
Open your mouth, Judith.
张开嘴妈妈来了就这样
Open your mouth. Mama's here. That's it.
那挺好的
That's good.
是的 你会安全的
Yes, you'll be safe.
你张开嘴 把它喝下去
You'll open your mouth. Drink it down.
咽下去妈妈在这里没事的 朱迪思
Swallow it down. Mama's here. It's okay, Judith.
妈妈来了 没事的
Mama's here. It's okay.
好的
Okay.
艾格尼丝
Agnes.
你已经尽力了
You have done all that you can.
我不会让她越界
I will not let her cross over.
奶奶 您有三个女儿 她们都被夺去了生命
Grandmama, you had three daughters that were taken.
他们是……
Were they...
她们像朱迪思吗？
Were they like Judith?
安妮七岁
Anne was seven.
另外两个还是婴儿
The other two were just babies.
他们身上都有肿胀 而且……
They all had swellings and...
像朱迪思一样发烧
...fever like Judith.
你妈妈想……
Your mother's trying to...
看好她的孩子
keep a grip on her child.
这行不通
It won't work.
给予的东西随时可能被收回
What is given may be taken away at any time.
我们绝不能放松警惕
We must never let our guard down.
永远不要把……视为理所当然
Never take for granted...
……我们孩子的心脏在跳动
...that our children's hearts beat,
它们呼吸着
that they draw breath,
他们行走、说话 而且……
that they walk and speak and...
……微笑、争论、玩耍
...smile, argue, play.
永远不要忘记 他们可能随时会离开
Never forget for a moment that they may be gone.
裘德
Jude.
别难过
Don't be sad.
你会康复的
You shall be well.
我不会
I shall not.
没有你 我做不到
Not without you.
它在这里
It's here.
裘德 你看到了吗？
Do you see it, Jude?
它在监视我们
It's watching us.
我会告诉它带我们俩一起去
I'll tell it to take us both.
我们一起去
We'll go together.
转身离开
Turn away.
它会犯错
It'll make a mistake.
它无法区分我们
It can't tell us apart.
朱迪思 跟我一起呼吸
Breathe with me, Judith.
我将我的生命献给你
I give you my life.
你会康复的
You shall be well.
朱迪思 我愿将我的生命献给你
I give you my life, Judith.
我会勇敢的
I'll be brave.
父亲 我会勇敢的
I'll be brave, Father.
我会勇敢的
I'll be brave.
父亲 我会勇敢的
I'll be brave, Father.
我会勇敢的
I'll be brave.
哇
Whoa.
尽快
Quick as you can.
哈姆内特
Hamnet.
哈姆内特 你不应该在这里
Hamnet, you're not supposed to be down here.
我得扶你上床睡觉
I need to take you up to bed.
哈姆内特
Hamnet.
哈姆内特？
Hamnet?
妈妈
Mama.
哈姆内特
Hamnet.
你必须张开嘴
You must open your mouth.
一切都会好起来的
All will be well.
他着火了
He's burning.
他快要烧起来了
He's burning up.
它不会粘住——它不会粘住！
It will not sti-- It will not stick!
一块石头那里有一块石头
A stone. There's a stone.
楼上有一块石头 中间有个洞
There's a stone upstairs with a hole in the middle of it.
放在他床边拿下来我需要它
By his bedside. Bring it down. I need it.
还有 嗯 呃 盐去拿盐
And, um, uh, salt. Get salt.
拿到手了你能送出去吗？
Get it. Can you give it?
你能帮我拿点盐来吗？有多少盐都行
Can you f-fetch me some salt, as much salt as you have.
水我们需要水
Water. We need water.
他……他太火辣了
He's... he's too hot.
他着火了
He's burning.
我的爱人妈妈来了
My love. Mama's here.
一切都会好起来的一切都会好起来的
All will be well. All will be well.
一切都会好起来的
All will be well.
哈姆内特 别害怕
Hamnet, don't be scared.
不必害怕
No need to be scared.
一切都会好起来的妈妈在这里
All will be well. Mommy's here.
妈妈在这里没事的
Mommy's here. It's okay.
妈妈来了
Mommy's here.
看我 妈妈在这里
Look at me. Mommy's here.
我永远、永远不会放你走
I will never, ever let you go.
你明白吗？
You understand?
我永远、永远不会放你走
I will never, ever let you go.
我爱你
I love you.
伊莱扎 把朱迪丝带到厨房去 让她待在那里
Eliza, take Judith to the kitchen and keep her there.
请！
Please!
他需要我！——待在那儿
- He needs me! -Stay there.
他需要我！
He needs me!
请！
Please!
瓦莱里安……
Valerian...
哈姆内特哈姆内特哈姆内特
Hamnet. Hamnet. Hamnet.
哈姆内特 你必须留下哈姆内特 求你了
Hamnet, you have to stay. Hamnet, please.
哈姆内特 求你了你必须留下来和我们在一起
Hamnet, please. You have to stay with us.
妈妈需要你我们需要你
Mama needs you. We need you.
停！够了！——留下来留下来 留下来
-Stop! Enough! - Stay with us. Stay, stay.
拜托了 哈姆内特哈姆内特 哈姆内特 哈姆内特
Please, Hamnet. Hamnet, Hamnet, Hamnet.
放开他！哈姆内特 求你了！
-Let him alone! - Hamnet, please!
你难道看不出来对他来说已经太晚了吗！
Can't you see that it's too late for him!
求求你了
Please, please.
哈姆内特？
Hamnet?
哈姆内特哈姆内特
Hamnet. Hamnet.
我的儿子走了
My son is gone.
我的儿子
My son.
我丢了我的……
I've lost my...
我看见了光 然后就睡不着了
I saw the light, and I couldn't sleep.
玛丽在此
MARY Here.
哦 孩子 不要
Oh, child, no.
- 不 不 不去睡觉吧- 不 不 让她留下来吧
- No, no, no. Go to bed. - No, no, let-let her stay.
都是我的错 妈妈
It is my fault, Mama.
是我的错——不 不
- It is my fault. - No. No.
朱迪思 这不是你的错
It is not your fault, Judith.
但他和我交换了位置
But he changed places with me.
他骗过了它
He tricked it.
他骗了什么？
He tricked what?
死亡
Death.
朱迪思
Judith.
当他来抓我的时候 他也跟着走了
It took him when it came for me.
永远不要再对任何人说这些话
Never say those words to anyone ever again.
你哥哥得了高烧 夺去了他的生命
The fever came for your brother, and it took him.
你想见他吗？
Do you wish to see him?
是的
Yes.
继续往前走 你可以看到他
Go on. You can see him.
真的是他吗？
Is it really him?
是的
Yes.
它——它看起来不像他
It-it doesn't look like him.
不
No.
不是他
It's not him.
它不是
It's not.
不是他
It's not him.
现在 现在 还没到早上呢
It-It's-it's not morning yet.
我们没有让他做好充分的准备
We haven't prepared him properly.
我来晚了吗？
Am I too late?
是你——父亲
- It's you. -Father.
是你
It's you.
这就是我
It's me.
他在哪儿？
Where is he?
在哪里……
Where is...
在哪里...
Where...
是我儿子
It's my boy.
我没看到
I didn't see it.
我应该更注意他的
I should've paid him more attention.
我一直以为被带走的是她
I always thought she was the one to be taken away
其实一直都是他
when all the while it was him.
我真是个傻瓜
I'm a fool.
不 任何人都无法救他
No, there's nothing anyone could have done to save him.
你已经尽力了
You did everything that you could.
当然 我做了
Of course I did.
你当时不在
You weren't here.
我愿意把我的心挖出来送给他
I would have cut my heart out and given it to him.
我愿意为他献出生命
I would have laid my life down on the ground for him.
我知道我知道——但没人会接受它
- I-I know. I know. - And no one would take it.
- 但是你…… - 不 你不知道
- But you... - No, you don't know.
你不知道你当时不在场
You don't know. You weren't here.
他死时极度痛苦
He died in agony.
我...
I...
他当时非常痛苦——艾格尼丝
- He was in agony. - Agnes.
他哭啊哭
He cried and he cried
他哭啊哭啊哭——艾格尼丝 别哭了 别哭了
- and he cried and he cried. - Agnes, stop, stop.
他幼小的身体疼痛难忍
And his little body was wracked in pain. -
不 别让我安静
No, don't shush me.
他吓坏了
He was so scared.
——你当时不在——我知道
- And you weren't here. - I know.
我尽了一切努力
I tried everything I could.
我知道你做到了
I know you did.
我尽力了……——你已经竭尽所能了
I tried... -You did everything that you could.
你已经尽力了
You did everything that you could.
一切
Everything.
艾格尼丝艾格尼丝
Agnes. Agnes.
我会捎信的 艾格尼丝
I will send word, Agnes.
你会传达消息吗？
You'll send word?
——给谁？——给你
- To whom? - To you.
- 我在这里 - 嗯
- I'm here. - Mm.
我的意思是 我到达伦敦后会通知大家
What I meant was that I shall send word when I reach London.
伦敦？
London?
我必须离开了
I must leave.
离开？你怎么能离开？
Leave? How can you leave?
艾格尼丝 世界瞬息万变
The world does simply not stand still, Agnes.
伦敦有人在等我
There are people waiting for me in London.
赛季即将开始
The season is about to begin,
我的公司应该很快就能从肯特郡返回了
and my company shall return from Kent any day now.
我现在得走了
I have to go now.
现在？
Now?
今天有一支旅行团出发
There's a traveling party leaving today,
他们还有一匹备用马 所以 是的
and they have a spare horse, so yeah.
照顾好孩子们 我一会儿就回来——
Look after the girls, and I will return to--
停止
Stop.
不
Don't.
走走
Go. Go.
当我数着时钟的时候
"When I do count the clock
“那是用来显示时间的
"that tells the time,
“看着勇敢的白昼沉入可怕的黑夜；
"And see the brave day sunk in hideous night;
“当我看到盛开已过的紫罗兰时
"When I behold the violet past prime,
“还有那银白色的黑色卷发；
"And sable curls all silver'd o'er with white;
当我看到高大的树木光秃秃的 叶子却不见了
"When lofty trees I see barren of leaves
“它曾为牛群遮挡烈日
"Which erst from the heat did canopy the herd,
“夏日的绿色都捆成了捆”
"And summer's green all girded up in sheaves
“抬着灵柩 长着白色而浓密的胡须；
"Borne on the bier with white and bristly beard;
那么 我该质疑你的美貌了
"Then of thy beauty do I question make,
“你必将遁入时间的荒芜之中
"Thou among the wastes of time must go,
“既然甜美和美丽本身就会消逝
"Since sweets and beauties do themselves forsake
“看着别人成长 他们却迅速死去；
"And die as fast as they see others grow;
“没有什么能抵挡时间的镰刀”
"And nothing gainst Time's scythe can make defense
留着后代 好在他带走你的时候勇敢面对他
Save breed, to brave him when he takes thee hence."
你会再读一遍吗？
Will you read it again?
不
No.
我已经读过三遍了
I've read it three times.
够了
That's enough.
我们互赠礼物吧？
Shall we do presents?
来自伦敦的礼物
Presents from London.
朱迪 给你一把梳子
A hair comb for you, Jude.
不过 你得小心点
Mind you, you'll have to be careful.
这是给你的 艾格尼丝
This is for you, Agnes.
——是红宝石吗？——嗯
- A ruby, is it? -Mm-hmm.
这是我见过的最好的
It's the finest I've ever seen.
大家都在谈论那栋新房子
Everyone's talking about the new house.
它是斯特拉特福德最大的
It's the biggest in Stratford.
房间太多了 很容易迷路
There are so many rooms. One could get lost.
苏珊娜 钥匙你保管好
You shall keep the keys, Susanna.
你要好好管理家务
You shall manage the house well.
妈妈 穿上它
Put it on, Mama.
巴塞洛缪带你看过新房子了吗？
Did Bartholomew show you the new house?
嗯
Mm-hmm.
你喜欢它？
Do you like it?
你为什么不亲自带我去看？
Why didn't you show me yourself?
你是不是怕我不走？
Were you afraid I wouldn't leave?
因为哈姆内特就死在这所房子里
'Cause Hamnet died here in this house.
你知道吗 我一直在想他在哪里
You know, I'm constantly wondering where he is.
或者他去了哪里
Or where he has gone.
无论我在做什么 我都会想：“他在哪里？”
Whatever I'm doing, I'm wondering, "Where is he?"
我的意思是 他不可能凭空消失
I mean, he can't have just vanished.
他只需要我找到他
All he needs is for me to find him.
他肯定在某个地方
He must be somewhere.
即使一年过去了 我仍然担心我会因此而发疯
I fear I may run mad with it, even now, a year on.
一年不算什么
A year is nothing.
每秒钟都是如此……
It's every second...
每时每刻 每一天
every minute, every day.
我们可能永远不会停止寻找他
We may never stop looking for him.
对不起 艾格尼丝
I'm sorry, Agnes.
你听到我说话了吗？我说过对不起 艾格尼丝
Did you hear me? I said that I'm sorry, Agnes.
——为了什么？——为了一切
- For what? - For everything.
你被那个地方困住了——因为……
- You're caught by that place. - For...
- 什么地方？ - 你脑海里的那个地方
- What place? - That place in your head.
现在 它对你来说比在任何其他地方都更加真实
It is now more real to you than anywhere else.
即使我们的孩子去世 也无法阻止你这样做
Not even the death of our child can keep you from it.
哈姆内特死了
Hamnet died.
死状极其惨烈
A horrible death.
你本应该在那里的
And you should have been there.
你本可以向他道别
You could have bid him farewell.
你看到了什么？
What do you see?
唔？
Hmm?
没有什么
Nothing.
没有什么？
Nothing?
什么也没有
Nothing at all.
那好吧
Oh, well.
你应该回伦敦
You should go back to London.
您不必为我们操心
You need not concern yourself with us.
没有你 我们也能过得很好
Get along just fine without you.
这有时是一个悖论
This was sometime a paradox,
但现在时间证明了这一点
but now the time gives it proof.
我曾经爱过你
I did love you once.
大人 您确实让我相信了这一点
Indeed, my lord, you made me believe so.
你不该相信我
You should not have believed me,
因为美德无法使我们的旧血统免受侵害……
for virtue cannot so inoculate our old stock for...
你不该相信我
You should not have believed me,
因为美德无法如此彻底地改变我们古老的血统
for virtue cannot so inoculate our old stock
但我们会好好享受这一切
but we shall relish of it.
我并不爱你
I loved you not.
我才是被欺骗的那个人
I was the more deceived.
去修道院吧
Get thee to a nunnery.
你为何要成为罪人的养育者？
Why wouldst thou be a breeder of sinners?
我本人为人冷漠诚实
I am myself indifferent honest,
但我却可以指责我做这样的事
but yet I could accuse me of such things
或许最好是……
that it were better to...
再次
Again.
去修道院吧
Get thee to a nunnery.
你为何要成为罪人的养育者？
Why wouldst thou be a breeder of sinners?
我本人为人坦诚冷漠 但是……
I am myself indifferent honest, but...
再说一遍“我本人是冷漠的诚实”再说一遍
Again. "I am myself indifferent honest." Again.
我本人为人冷漠诚实
I am myself indifferent honest,
但是 我却可以指责我做这样的事 这样反而更好
but yet I could accuse me of such things that it were better
我的母亲并没有生我——再说一遍
- my mother had not borne me. - Again.
我本人……
I, myself...
再次
Again.
我本人则漠不关心……
I, myself, am indifferent...
我就是我
"I am myself."
我本人为人冷漠诚实
I am myself indifferent honest,
但我却可以指责我做了那样的事……
but yet I could accuse me of such things that it were...
再次
Again.
但我却可以指责我做了那样的事……
But yet I could accuse me of such things that it were...
再次！
Again!
我本人为人冷漠诚实
I am myself indifferent honest,
但我却可以指责我犯下这样的错误……
but yet I could accuse me of such...
你只是在重复这些词而已！
You are simply mouthing the words!
我本人为人冷漠诚实
I am myself indifferent honest,
但我却可以指责我做这样的事
but yet I could accuse me of such things
真希望我母亲当初没生我
that it were better my mother had not borne me.
我非常骄傲、充满复仇心、野心勃勃
I am very proud, revengeful, ambitious,
更多犯罪机会摆在我面前
with more offenses at my beck
我有很多想法想把它们放进去
than I have thoughts to put them in,
发挥想象力赋予它们形状 或者给它们时间去演绎它们
imagination to give them shape or time to act them in.
那么 像我这样的人该怎么办呢？
Now, what should such fellows as I do
在天地之间爬行？
crawling between heaven and earth?
我们都是彻头彻尾的恶棍
We are arrant knaves all.
不要相信我们任何人
Believe none of us.
去修道院吧再一次
Go thy ways to a nunnery. Again.
成为……
To be...
……或者不……
...or not to be...
……这就是问题所在：
...that is the question:
无论从精神层面来说 忍受是否更高尚
Whether 'tis nobler in the mind to... suffer
种种攻击和伤害……
The slings and arrows of...
……惊人的财富……
...outrageous fortune...
...或者...
...Or...
……拿起武器反抗……
...to take arms against a...
……苦难之海
...sea of troubles,
而通过反对……
And by opposing...
……结束他们
...end them.
♪ 我祈祷那些树 ♪
♪ I pray that those trees ♪
♪ 我会把我的孩子还给我 ♪
♪ Will return my boy ♪
♪ 为了 ♪
♪ For ♪
♪ 可爱的小知更鸟 ♪
♪ Sweet bonny Robin ♪
♪ 这就是我所有的快乐♪
♪ Is all my joy. ♪
艾格尼丝？
Agnes?
我……我当时在城里 而且……
I... I was in town, and I...
我想来拜访你
I thought I would pay you a visit.
听到约翰去世的消息 我感到非常难过
I was very sorry to hear about John's passing.
你丈夫怎么样了？
How's your husband?
失去父亲是一件……是一件非常可怕的事情
It's a... it's a terrible thing to lose one's father.
他很好
He's well.
他很忙 正在筹备一部喜剧
He's very busy. He's preparing a comedy.
他的新剧不是喜剧
His new play is not a comedy.
真是一场悲剧
It's a tragedy.
但你知道这一点
But you knew that.
全镇的人都在谈论这件事
Everyone in town is talking about it.
我早就警告过你不要嫁给他
I did warn you about marrying him.
别假装你关心我
Don't pretend that you care for me.
你不是我的母亲 也从来都不是
You are not my mother, and you never were.
你好 艾格尼丝
Good day, Agnes.
他已经好几个月没跟我们说话了
He's not spoken to us for months.
他怎么能……
How could he...
他怎么可能不告诉我们呢？
How could he not tell us?
你难道不好奇里面装的是什么吗？
Do you not wonder what is in it?
在什么方面？
In what?
这部剧
The play.
你在找谁？
Who are you looking for?
威廉·莎士比亚
William Shakespeare.
我们是他来自斯特拉特福德的家人
We're his family from Stratford.
上楼去他住在阁楼里
Go up the stairs. He lives in the attic.
为什么斯特拉特福德拥有最大房子的人会这样做呢？
Why would the man with the largest house in Stratford
住在这里吗？
be living here?
我不明白
I don't understand.
我当时想……
I thought...
我以为他……
I thought he...
我该怎么办？
What shall I do?
保持开放的心态
Keep your heart open.
谁在那儿？——不 回答我：
-Who's there? -Nay, answer me:
站起来 展现自我！
stand and unfold yourself!
国王万岁！
Long live the king!
贝尔纳多？
Bernardo?
如果你真的遇到了霍雷肖和马塞勒斯
If you do meet Horatio and Marcellus,
我的竞争对手们 让他们赶紧行动吧
The rivals to my watch, bid them make haste.
我好像听到了他们的声音站起来！
I think I hear them. Stand, ho!
谁在那儿？
Who's there?
这东西今晚又出现了吗？
Has this thing appeared again tonight?
我什么也没看见——霍雷肖说……
- I have seen nothing. -Horatio says...
他们在谈论什么？
What are they talking about?
这一切跟我儿子有什么关系？
What has any of this to do with my son? -
这些人很害怕
These men are frightened.
什么？
Of what?
他们警惕着鬼魂
They watch for a ghost.
鬼？
Ghost?
……然后铃声响起……
...The bell then beating one...
和平 断绝关系！
Peace, break thee off!
瞧瞧它又出现了！
Look where it comes again!
就像那位已故的国王一样
In the same figure, like the king that's dead.
看 它悄悄溜走了！
See, it stalks away!
那是他
That was him.
那是威尔
That was Will.
他没参演——不 不
- He's not in the play. - No, no.
那是威尔的鬼魂
It was Will as a ghost.
我们最后的国王 他的形象此刻才显现在我们面前
Our last king, Whose image but now appeared to us,
被迫应战；我们英勇的哈姆雷特……
Was dared to the combat; our valiant Hamlet...
村庄
Hamlet.
你听到了吗……你听到了吗？
Did you hear... did you hear that?
是的
Yes.
他们喊出了他的名字
They said his-- they said his name.
艾格尼丝
Agnes.
艾格尼丝 等等——让开！
- Agnes, wait. - Out of my way!
请安静
Please be quiet.
等等 他们刚才提到他的名字了吗？嗯？
Wait, did they say his name? Huh?
不要让自己难过
Do not upset yourself.
为什么——他为什么要用自己的名字？
Why is-- Why did he use his name?
我不认识他——男：安静
- I don't know him. - -MAN: Quiet.
……并且根据我的建议
...and by my advice,
让我们把今晚所见所闻分享出来
Let us impart what we have seen tonight
致年轻的王子……
Unto the young prince...
你敢念我儿子的名字试试！
Don't you dare pronounce my son's name!
安静的！
Quiet!
……对我们来说很愚蠢 我会和他谈谈
...dumb to us, will speak to him.
虽然我们亲爱的兄弟去世的消息尚未公布
Though yet of our dear brother's death,
记忆是绿色的
The memory be green,
然而 迄今为止 谨慎与自然的斗争仍在继续
Yet so far hath discretion fought with nature
愿我们以最深切的悲痛缅怀他
That we with wisest sorrow think on him,
与我们对自身的记忆一同存在
Together with remembrance of ourselves.
我一分钟也不想再待下去参与这场闹剧了
I will not stay a minute longer to be a part of this jest.
等一下稍等片刻——不
- Wait. One moment. - No.
我想回家——我的表兄哈姆雷特
- I want to go home. -...my cousin Hamlet,
还有我的儿子……
and my son...
为什么乌云依然笼罩着你？
How is it that the clouds still hang on you?
善良的哈姆雷特 褪去你那阴郁的色彩吧
Good Hamlet, cast thy nighted color off.
不要永远用你那蒙着面纱的双眼
Do not for ever with thy vailed lids
在尘土中寻找你高贵的父亲
Seek for thy noble father in the dust.
凡有生命的 终将消亡
All that lives must die,
穿越自然 通往永恒
Passing through nature to eternity.
哎呀 夫人 这很常见
Ay, madam, it is common.
但我内心深处有一些东西可以证明这一点
But I have that within which passes show.
这些不过是苦难的外在表现和伪装
These are but the trappings and the suits of woe.
坚持不懈地表达顽固的哀悼
To persevere In obstinate condolement
这是一种不敬神的顽固行为
is a course of impious stubbornness.
这是不男子汉的悲伤
'Tis unmanly grief.
它展现了一种通往天堂最错误的意志
It shows a will most incorrect to heaven.
哦
Oh.
这也太硬了 肉体也会融化
This too, too solid flesh would melt,
融化并凝结成露水
Thaw and resolve itself into a dew.
或者说 永恒者并未定下这个结论
Or that the Everlasting had not fixed
他反对自杀的教条
His canon gainst self-slaughter.
这是一个没有除草的花园 却长出了种子；
'Tis an unweeded garden That grows to seed;
事物本性卑劣肮脏 仅仅拥有它
things rank and gross in nature Possess it merely.
事情竟然会发展到这种地步
That it should come to this.
但两个月过去了——
But two months dead--
不 没那么多 不到两个——
nay, not so much, not two--
如此杰出的国王 真是令人敬佩
So excellent a king, that was to this
许珀里翁变成了……一个萨提尔
Hyperion to a... a satyr.
你将引领我到哪里去？
Whither wilt thou lead me?
说吧我不会再往前走了
Speak. I'll go no further.
我是你父亲的灵
I am thy father's spirit,
注定要在某个期限内行走于黑夜之中
Doomed for a certain term to walk the night,
而这一天 他只能在火中禁食
And for the day confined to fast in fires.
我的时间快到了
My hour is almost come
当我坠入硫磺灼热的火焰中
When I to sulfurous and tormenting flames
我必须亲自上阵
Must render up myself.
唉 可怜的鬼魂不 别同情我……
- Alas, poor ghost. - No, pity me not...
但请认真聆听我将要讲述的内容
...but lend thy serious hearing To what I shall unfold.
列表
List.
清单 哦 清单
List, oh, list.
如果你曾经爱你的父亲……
If thou didst ever thy father love...
我的天哪
Oh, God.
但很柔和 我觉得我闻到了清晨空气的气息
But soft, methinks I scent the morning air.
让我独自待一会儿我在果园里安睡
Brief let me be. Sleeping within my orchard.
在我安稳的时刻 你叔叔偷走了
Upon my secure hour, thy uncle stole
用小瓶盛着被诅咒的赫波娜汁液
With juice of cursed hebona in a vile,
倾泻而入我的耳畔
Within the porches of my ears did pour
麻风病蒸馏液……
The leprous distillment...
……其影响与人类的鲜血有着如此深重的仇恨
...whose effect Holds such an enmity with blood of man
它像水银一样迅速地流淌
That swift as quicksilver it courses through
身体的天然通道和通道
The natural gates and alleys of the body.
它突然变得旺盛起来
And with a sudden vigor it doth posset
还有凝乳 就像……
And curd, like...
…急切地将粪便排入牛奶中
...eager droppings into milk,
清澈而健康的血液
The thin and wholesome blood.
我的也是
So did it mine.
一只最快吠叫起来的狗……
A most instant tetter barked about...
……最像拉扎尔 有令人作呕的硬皮
...Most lazar-like, with vile and loathsome crust,
我全身光滑
All my smooth body.
哦 太糟糕了
Oh, horrible.
哦 太可怕了简直太可怕了
Oh, horrible. Most horrible.
如果你天性如此 就不要容忍它……
If thou hast nature in thee, bear it not...
他和我们的儿子互换了位置
He has swapped places with our son.
看着我
Look at me.
萤火虫表明晨曦即将到来
The... the glowworm shows the matin to be near,
于是 他那无力的火焰开始黯淡下来
And 'gins to pale his uneffectual fires.
我的孩子
My boy.
再见
Adieu.
记住账号
Remember me.
生存还是毁灭
To be, or not to be,
这是个问题
that is the question.
苦难是否在精神层面上更高尚
Whether 'tis nobler in the mind to suffer
命运的无情捉弄
The slings and arrows of outrageous fortune,
或者拿起武器对抗重重困难
Or to take arms against a sea of troubles
通过反对 终结它们
And, by opposing, end them.
死亡 睡眠
To die, to sleep,
不再
No more.
以睡眠来结束
And by a sleep, to say we end
心痛和千百次自然冲击
The heartache and the thousand natural shocks
那肉体是——的继承者 这是圆满的
That flesh is heir to-- 'tis a consummation
虔诚地祈愿
Devoutly to be wished.
死亡
To die,
入睡 或许会做梦
To sleep, perchance to dream.
哎 问题就在这里
Ay, there's the rub.
因为在那死亡的沉睡中 会有哪些梦境降临？
For in that sleep of death, what dreams may come
当我们离开这尘世的轮回之时
When we have shuffled off this mortal coil
这值得我们深思
Must give us pause.
尊重是存在的
There's the respect
长寿就是一场灾难
That makes calamity of so long life.
谁愿承受时光的鞭笞和嘲弄？
Who would bear the whips and scorns of time,
压迫者错了
The oppressor's wrong,
骄傲之人的蔑视
the proud man's contumely,
被鄙视的爱情带来的痛苦 法律的拖延
The pangs of despised love, the law's delay,
官职的傲慢和蔑视
The insolence of office, and the spurns
那份对不值得接受的人的耐心和价值
That patient merit of the unworthy take,
当他自己能够安息的时候
When he himself might his quietus make
用裸露的锥子？
With a bare bodkin?
谁会承担包袱？
Who would fardels bear,
在疲惫的生活下呻吟流汗
To grunt and sweat under a weary life,
但那是对死后事物的恐惧
But that the dread of something after death,
未被发现的国度 其起源
The undiscovered country from whose bourn
没有旅行者返回 这令遗嘱感到困惑
No traveler returns, puzzles the will,
这使我们宁愿忍受这些苦难……
And makes us rather bear those ills...
警惕！
En garde!
一！
One!
不不！
No! No!
大获成功 实至名归！
A hit, a palpable hit!
我们的儿子一定会赢！
Our son shall win!
又来了！
Well, again!
格特鲁德 不要喝酒
Gertrude, do not drink.
又一首热门歌曲！你们觉得呢？
Another hit! What say you?
现在就来吧！
Have at you now!
女王怎么样？
How does the queen?
她看到他们流血就晕倒了
She swoons to see them bleed.
不 不 是饮料 是饮料！
No, no, the drink, the drink!
哦 我亲爱的哈姆雷特
Oh, my dear Hamlet.
我中毒了
I am poisoned.
哦 邪恶！
Oh, villainy!
嚯 把门锁上！
Ho, let the door be locked!
背叛！去寻找它！
Treachery! Seek it out!
就在这里 哈姆雷特
It is here, Hamlet.
哈姆雷特 你被杀了
Hamlet, thou art slain.
世界上没有任何药物能治好你
No medicine in the world can do thee good.
你里面连半小时的生命都没有
In thee, there is not half an hour's life.
都怪国王！
The king's to blame!
伤口也中毒了吗？
The point envenomed, too?
那么 毒液 开始你的工作吧！
Then, venom, to thy work!
来吧 你这乱伦、杀人、该死的丹麦人！
Here, thou incestuous, murderous, damned Dane!
喝...
Drink...
把这药水喝下去！
Drink off this potion!
你的联盟在这里吗？
Is thy union here?
跟着我妈妈
Follow my mother.
我死了
I am dead.
你活着
Thou livest.
举报我和我的案情
Report me and my cause aright
致那些不满现状的人
To the unsatisfied.
如果你曾将我放在心上
If thou didst ever hold me in thy heart,
暂时离开幸福
Absent thee from felicity awhile,
在这残酷的世界里 痛苦地喘息吧
And in this harsh world draw thy breath in pain
讲述我的故事
To tell my story.
我死了！
I die!
这剧毒彻底吞噬了我的灵魂
The potent poison quite o'ercrows my spirit.
其余时间一片寂静
The rest is silence.
♪我的知更鸟将飞向绿林♪
♪ My Robin to the greenwood will go ♪
♪橡树和白蜡树所在的地方♪
♪ Where the oak and the ash ♪
♪ 荆棘丛生 ♪
♪ And the briars do grow ♪
♪我的爱人境况如何？♪
♪ How fares my love ♪
♪ 夜幕降临 ♪
♪ As the darkness falls ♪
♪ 就在那里 ♪
♪ There within ♪
♪ 那些错综复杂的墙壁？ ♪
♪ Those tangled walls? ♪
♪我的爱人境况如何？♪
♪ How fares my love ♪
♪ 夜幕降临 ♪
♪ As the darkness falls ♪
♪ 就在那里 ♪
♪ There within ♪
♪ 那些错综复杂的墙壁？ ♪
♪ Those tangled walls? ♪
♪ 绿林就在附近 ♪
♪ The greenwood is near ♪
♪ 而绿林很远 ♪
♪ And the greenwood is far ♪
♪ 以及诸多危险 ♪
♪ And many a danger ♪
♪ 那里发生了一件人事 ♪
♪ Befalls a man there ♪
♪ 我祈祷那些树 ♪
♪ I pray that those trees ♪
♪ 我会把我的孩子还给我 ♪
♪ Will return my boy ♪
♪ 献给甜美可爱的罗宾 ♪
♪ For sweet bonny Robin ♪
♪ 这就是我所有的快乐 ♪
♪ Is all my joy ♪
♪ 我祈祷那些树 ♪
♪ I pray that those trees ♪
♪ 我会把我的孩子还给我 ♪
♪ Will return my boy ♪
♪ 献给甜美可爱的罗宾 ♪
♪ For sweet bonny Robin ♪
♪ 这就是我所有的快乐♪
♪ Is all my joy. ♪